الشيخ عبد الرحمن قرية سورية تتبع ناحية جنديرس منطقة عفرين في
ريف حلب الشمالي.
Sheikh Abdul Rahman is a Syrian village belonging to the
Jindires sub-district, Afrin district, in the northern
countryside of Aleppo.
وهي تقع على يمين الطريق الواصل ما بين عفرين وناحية جنديرس،
It is located on the right side of the road connecting Afrin
and the Jindires sub-district,
وأيضاً تبعد عن منطقة عفرين 13 كيلومتر باتجاه الغرب.
and it is also 13 kilometers away from the Afrin district
towards the west.
جولتنا لهالأسبوع رح تكون من قرية الشيخ عبد الرحمن التابعة
لناحية جنديرس.
Our tour this week will be from the village of Sheikh Abdul
Rahman, which belongs to the Jindires sub-district.
تابعونا.
Stay with us.
الشيخ عبد الرحمن، قرية سورية تتبع ناحية جنديرس منطقة عفرين
في ريف حلب الشمالي،
Sheikh Abdul Rahman is a Syrian village belonging to the
Jindires sub-district, Afrin district, in the northern
countryside of Aleppo.
أقيمت في منطقة منبسطة محاطة بغابات الزيتون على يمين الطريق
الواصل بين عفرين وجنديرس،
It was established in a flat area surrounded by olive
forests on the right side of the road connecting Afrin and
Jindires.
يمر نهر الشيخ عبد الرحمن في الشمال والغرب منها،
The Sheikh Abdul Rahman River passes through its north and
west,
ويتابع سيره جنوباً باتجاه قريتي تل حمو والفريرية ويصب في نهر
عفرين.
and it continues its course southwards towards the villages
of Tal Hamo and Al-Fureriya, and flows into the Afrin River.
إلى الغرب من القرية تقع قرية كوجامان، وإلى الشمال منها تقع
قرى قيلان وجولاقان وخرزان،
To the west of the village lies the village of Kojaman, and
to its north lie the villages of Qilan, Julaqan, and
Kharzan,
وإلى الشرق من قرية الشيخ عبد الرحمن تقع قرية تلف.
and to the east of Sheikh Abdul Rahman village lies the
village of Talaf.
قبل أكثر من 100 عام كانت القرية عبارة عن مساكن مبنية من
الطين والأسقف الخشبية واسطبلات للحيوانات.
More than 100 years ago, the village consisted of houses
built of mud and wooden roofs, and stables for animals.
على جانب طريق عفرين - جنديرس كان يوجد في القرية خان ومحلات
تجارية،
On the side of the Afrin - Jindires road, there used to be
an inn and commercial shops in the village,
معدة لراحة واستقبال المسافرين من كلس وأنطاكيا إلى حلب
وبالعكس.
prepared for the rest and reception of travelers from Kilis
and Antakya to Aleppo and vice versa.
ومن أشهر عائلات القرية، بيت سيدو، وبيت إيبش، ومدور، وجمو،
وبطال بكر، وعائلات من عشيرة العميرات العربية.
Among the most famous families of the village are the Sido
family, the Ibish family, Mdawwar, Jamo, Battal Bakr, and
families from the Arab Al-Omeirat tribe.
يبلغ عدد عائلات القرية حالياً 130 عائلة.
The number of families in the village is currently 130
families.
يعتمد أهالي القرية في معيشتهم على الزراعة وتربية الحيوانات،
The people of the village depend on agriculture and animal
husbandry for their livelihood,
حيث يغطي الزيتون مساحة 99% من الأراضي.
as olives cover an area of 99% of the lands.
يعاني أهالي القرية من عدم توفر الماء والكهرباء، وعدم وجود
نظام للصرف الصحي.
The people of the village suffer from the lack of water and
electricity, and the absence of a sewage system.
من أهم المعالم فيها، مزار الشيخ عبد الرحمن، والجسر القديم
المبني فوق النهر.
Among the most important landmarks in it are the shrine of
Sheikh Abdul Rahman, and the old bridge built over the
river.
العم عبدو مدور أبو فريد، 90 سنة، هو أكبر شخصية موجودة في
قرية الشيخ عبد الرحمن.
Uncle Abdo Mdawwar Abu Farid, 90 years old, is the oldest
figure in the village of Sheikh Abdul Rahman.
ويمكن مرت عليه معظم المراحل التاريخية اللي مرت على هالقرية،
And probably most of the historical stages that passed
through this village have passed by him,
وهو يعتبر من العلامات الفارقة المميزة لقرية الشيخ عبد
الرحمن.
and he is considered one of the distinct landmarks of Sheikh
Abdul Rahman village.
رح نكون معكم بهالفقرة الصغيرة بزيارة لبيته لنتعرف عليه ونشوف
أبعاد هالشخصية الظريفة اللي حملت يعني، تلاوين الأطياف اللي
مرت على هالقرية، تابعونا.
We will be with you in this short segment on a visit to his
home to get to know him and see the dimensions of this
pleasant personality that carried, I mean, the colors of the
spectrums that passed through this village. Stay with us.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام أهلاً وسهلاً شرفتونا تفضلوا.
Peace be upon you too, welcome, you have honored us, please
come in.
عمي أبو فريد شلونك؟
Uncle Abu Farid, how are you?
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
شلون صحتك؟
How is your health?
أهلاً وسهلاً حياكم الله.
Welcome, may God greet you.
أهلاً مختار.
Welcome, Mukhtar.
أهلاً أستاذي أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome, my teacher, welcome.
لا شرف اقعد انت بالنص هنا.
No, please come sit in the middle here.
شرف مختار.
Please come, Mukhtar.
أهلاً عمي أبو فريد.
Welcome, uncle Abu Farid.
إيوه.
Yes.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
الحمد لله رب العالمين.
How is your health?
Praise be to God, Lord of the Worlds.
احكي لي إيش في عندك أولاد؟
Tell me, how many children do you have?
والله البركة عندي ستة وبنتين... ثمانية.
Well, it's a blessing, I have six boys and two girls...
eight.
ما شاء الله، الله يخليهم.
Mashallah, may God protect them.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
شقد عمر الكبير؟
How old is the eldest?
الكبير شقد عمره؟ فريد.
The eldest, how old is he? Farid.
فريد إيوه.
Farid, yes.
شي 55... 57... 57 هيك شي.
About 55... 57... 57, something like that.
57 سنة.
57 years old.
احكي لي هلق أنا حسب ما عرفت إنه إنت يعني عشت تقريباً كل شي
مر على هالضيعة.
Tell me now, according to what I've learned, you've lived
through almost everything that passed through this village.
إيوه.
Yes.
يعني إنت كنت على زمان خليل آغا.
I mean, you were here during the time of Khalil Agha.
إيوه.
Yes.
وكنت على زمان الفرنسيين.
And you were here during the time of the French.
إيوه.
Yes.
وعلى زمان الإنجليز لما اجوا لهون ومشان الجسر... احكي لي عن
ذكرياتك.
And during the time of the British when they came here and
for the bridge... tell me about your memories.
حتى جابوا دبابات أنا شفتهم.
They even brought tanks, I saw them.
شفت؟
You saw?
ما خلوا، إجوا دبابات كان صغار.
They didn't leave anything out, there were small tanks that
came.
احكي لي عن الضيعة أيام ما كانت لسا صغيرة.
Tell me about the village back when it was still small.
كان والله أول فقراء كلهم.
By God, everyone was poor at first.
وما في حدا له بيت، كل واحد بالعمارة، بالتراب عمروه.
And no one had a house, everyone built their building with
dirt.
وجابوا قش من أنطاكيا، عم بيجيبوا من الريحانية كان، يحطوا
عليه.
And they brought straw from Antakya, they used to bring it
from Reyhanli, to put it on top.
وما في لا واحد شجرة زيتون، حتى الدار ما لهم، الدار ساكنين
فيه تبع الآغا كان.
And there wasn't a single olive tree, even the house wasn't
theirs, the house they lived in belonged to the Agha.
البيوت كانت عم بتقول من إيش كانت البيوت يعمروها؟
You were saying about the houses, what did they build the
houses from?
البيوت من طين.
The houses were from mud.
من طين، وكانوا يحطوا عليها قش...
From mud, and they used to put straw on it...
إي قش وهذول.
Yes, straw and those things.
عواميد، عواميد.
Columns, columns.
عامود. خشب. عامود وسقف تراب وقش ومشان يحموا حالهم من
الشتي... إيوه هيك.
A column. Wood. A column, and a roof of dirt and straw to
protect themselves from the winter... yes, like that.
إنت بهديك الفترة شقد كان عمرك؟
How old were you at that time?
عمري كان 15، 14 هيك شي.
I was 15, 14, something like that.
إيش كنت تشتغل؟
What did you use to work as?
كان أنا أول شي بشتغل، بتعلم عالتركتور.
At first, I was working, learning on the tractor.
إجا تركتور، ما في مازوت، عالكاز.
A tractor came, there was no diesel, it ran on kerosene.
التراكتورات اللي اجوا كانوا يشتغلوا عالكاز؟
The tractors that came used to run on kerosene?
عالكاز.
On kerosene.
عند الآغا؟
At the Agha's?
عند الآغا لكان أنا عندي وين!
At the Agha's, of course, where else would I have one!
تفلح له أراضي الآغا؟
Plowing the Agha's lands for him?
إيوه.
Yes.
إيوه إيوه.
Yes, yes.
احكي لي لما اجوا الفرنسيين لهون مشان الجسر.
Tell me when the French came here for the bridge.
مشان الجسر أنا بعيني ما شفت شي.
For the bridge, I didn't see anything with my own eyes.
بس شفت فرنسا... أنا عم بقول شفت فرنسا دعموه للجسر.
But I saw France... I'm saying I saw France reinforcing the
bridge.
تدعيم اللي دعموها للجسر أنت لحقته بعدين معلمينكم...
The reinforcement that they did to the bridge, you caught up
with it later...
الدعم كان عم بيشتغلوا فيه... بس هداك عم بيشتغلوا فيه أنا
بالليل... كان إنجليز.
The reinforcement they were working on... but that one they
were working on, I was there at night... it was the British.
ها، معناتها بعد الفرنسيين، انسحبوا، إجوا الإنجليز دعموا
الجسر مشان تمشي دباباتهم وتكون الجسر قوية...
Ah, that means after the French, they withdrew, the British
came and reinforced the bridge so their tanks could pass and
the bridge would be strong...
إيوه، وحجرات أسود كان بالشاكوش كان بيكسروه.
Yes, and there were black stones they used to break with a
hammer.
إنجليز.
The British.
احكي لي يعني، بعدين... أنت رويت لي قبل ما نصور إنه الأرمن
اجوا لهون وعا جولاقان، استصلحوا الأراضي هي وفلحوها ونظفوها
وجروا المي.
Tell me, I mean, afterwards... you told me before we filmed
that the Armenians came here and to Julaqan, they reclaimed
these lands, plowed them, cleaned them, and brought water.
يا سيدي جولاقان ما في أراضي كان، كله جبل.
Sir, there were no lands in Julaqan, it was all mountains.
أرمن اجا لهون، مشان تراكتورات يشتغلوا، اشتغلوا كل هالشي هاد
من هون لدير بلوط.
The Armenians came here, so the tractors could work, they
worked all of this from here to Deir Ballut.
من الخليل لجنب الحدود.
From Al-Khalil to near the border.
كله أجروه هن؟
They rented it all?
كله سهل وبتراكتور جنزير متل دبابات، أربع خمسة كانوا، أخذوا
بالإيجار.
All the plains, and with a tracked tractor like tanks, there
were four or five, they took it for rent.
وجابوا مي من من برج عبدالو لهون؟
And they brought water from Burj Abdalo to here?
إيوه... لا برج عبدالو لا، مي من الزيارة.
Yes... no, not Burj Abdalo, water from Al-Ziyarah.
من الزيارة، مي من الزيارة.
From Al-Ziyarah, water from Al-Ziyarah.
إيوه.
Yes.
برج عبدالو هداك غير موضوع.
Burj Abdalo, that is a different story.
داك غير.
That's different.
تبع الغزاوية.
The one for Ghazawiya.
إيوه، برج عبدالو كان يجي لوين؟ كوكبة.
Yes, Burj Abdalo used to come to where? Kokaba.
لكوكبة.
To Kokaba.
إيوه يوصل لكوكبة إيوه.
Yes, it reached Kokaba, yes.
احكي لي عن صحتك.
Tell me about your health.
صحتك شلونها؟
How is your health?
صحتي أنا عمري قبل ما أتجوز، بتعرف كم كيلو بجي؟ 57.
My health, before I got married, do you know how many kilos
I weighed? 57.
هلق عمري صاير 90، إيش عم بجي؟ 52.
Now my age is 90, how much do I weigh? 52.
إي نفس الشي.
Yes, it's the same thing.
وأنا مرض لسا ما شفت، دق ما ساويت، حباية ما بشرب، إبرة ما
باكل.
And I haven't seen an illness yet, I haven't gotten an
injection, I don't take a pill, I don't get a shot.
ما شايف دكتور ولا شايف شي.
You haven't seen a doctor and you haven't seen anything.
ما شاء الله.
Mashallah.
الله يعطيك العافية عمي أبو فريد.
May God give you health, uncle Abu Farid.
أهلاً وسهلاً شرفتونا.
Welcome, you have honored us.
شكراً إلك. الله يكرمك ويعافيك يا رب.
Thank you. May God bless you and grant you health.
حنوني يا عمي أبو فريد؟
Are you affectionate, uncle Abu Farid?
أهلاً على عيني.
Welcome, upon my eyes.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الحمد لله شلونك انت؟
Praise be to God, how are you?
شلون صحتك؟
How is your health?
الحمد لله، ولا أنا مرضانه وميتة.
Praise be to God, but I am sick and dying.
عجب أبوسه ومليح؟
Shall I kiss him, is it okay?
ليه؟
Why?
لا ما بتوافقي، ما بتوافقي.
No, you don't agree, you don't agree.
ههه.
Hahaha.
طولي بالك، طولي بالك شوي، شلونك؟
Be patient, be patient a little bit, how are you?
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
شلون صحتك؟
How is your health?
ولا أنا مرضانه وميتة.
Well, I am sick and dying.
سلامتك، ايش عم بيجعك؟
Get well soon, what is hurting you?
Me'dê min, gişkî.
My stomach, everything.
قسك؟
Your back?
E.
Yes.
سلامتك سلامتك. شقد عمرك؟
Get well soon, get well soon. How old are you?
Xwedê dizane, ez nizanim.
God knows, I don't know.
خدي بتعرف أنا بعرف.
God knows, I know.
فوق 70.
Over 70.
فوق 70؟ أنا شايف عمرك 50، إنت عم تكبريها مشان ما تتجوزي!
Over 70? I see your age as 50, you are making yourself older
so you don't get married!
Na limin xwedê xayo, ez ditirsim mîna Emin e.
No, by God, brother, I am afraid he is like security.
متل إيش؟ متل أمن؟
Like what? Like security?
متل أمن. بتعرف إيش بسوي؟ بقول لي بدي أروح أشتكي عند جيش
الحر.
Like security. Do you know what he does? He tells me I will
go complain to the Free Army.
معقول؟
Seriously?
بقول بدي أقول هذا حزبي، بدي أموت حالي!
He says I will say this one is a party member, I want to
kill myself!
ههه.
Hahaha.
شلونك؟ كم سنة عشتي معه؟
How are you? How many years have you lived with him?
إيمت تجوزنا؟
When did we get married?
من إيمت يعني؟
Since when, I mean?
من زمان، هو بيعرف.
Since a long time ago, he knows.
60 سنة؟
60 years?
صار له، إي.
It's been that long, yes.
طيب بهالستين سنة شلون كان معك؟ منيح؟
Okay, in these 60 years, how was he with you? Good?
خايو والله العظيم إش قد إجا، قال إلهن بدي هازلمة هاد.
Brother, by Almighty God, however many came, I told them I
want this man.
حبيتي كتير؟ حبيتيه كتير؟ حنون عليكي؟ بالله حنون؟
Did you love him a lot? Did you love him a lot? Is he
affectionate with you? Really affectionate?
مو حنون.
He is not affectionate.
ما حنون؟
Not affectionate?
لا.
No.
ليه؟
Why?
ما بعرف.
I don't know.
ليش، ليش قلبك قاسي؟
Why, why is your heart cruel?
قاسي، بدي أتجوز وما بخلي.
Cruel, I want to get married and he doesn't let me.
بدها تتجوز!
She wants to get married!
قلنا لها بدك تتجوزي تزوجي.
We told her if you want to get married, get married.
إذا تجوزت معلش؟
Is it fine if she gets married?
معلش خلي تتجوز.
It's fine, let her get married.
خلص؟
Is it settled?
إي خلص.
Yes, it's settled.
إنت إلك ولادك وإيش بدك فيه؟
You have your children, what do you want with him?
إيوه.
Yes.
لا، أنا ما بزعلك، أنا معك، طولي بالك.
No, I won't upset you, I am on your side, be patient.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يخلي لي إياك.
May God protect you for me.
الله يسلمك يا ابني.
May God keep you safe, my son.
الله يطول بعمرك ويشدك بالعافية.
May God prolong your life and bless you with health.
الله يعافيك الله يخلي ولادك.
May God grant you health, may God protect your children.
يا رب، شكراً إلك.
Amen, thank you.
تاريخ قرية الشيخ عبد الرحمن ما هو تاريخ بعيد كتير،
The history of the village of Sheikh Abdul Rahman is not a
very distant history,
يمكن بيزيد عن 100 سنة بشوي،
it might be a little over 100 years,
لأنه هالضيعة كانت بالأصل عبارة عن كروم وبساتين تتبع لآل سيدو
ميمه،
because this village was originally vineyards and orchards
belonging to the Sido Mimeh family,
اللي هن ملاكين الأراضي في جولاقان وعدد من القرى في هيدي
المنطقة.
who are the landowners in Julaqan and a number of villages
in this region.
وكان يسكن فيها فلاحين وعمال يشتغلوا بالمرابعة مع بيت سيدو
ميمه.
And farmers and workers used to live in it, working as
sharecroppers with the Sido Mimeh family.
لنحكي عن تاريخ هالضيعة رح نكون مع المختار آزاد سيدو،
To talk about the history of this village, we will be with
the Mukhtar Azad Sido,
ليحكي لنا عن تاريخ هالضيعة الحلوة وإيش مر عليها مراحل
تاريخية، وأهم هالمعالم هيدي.
to tell us about the history of this beautiful village and
the historical stages it went through, and the most
important of these landmarks.
تابعونا.
Stay with us.
مختار الله يعطيك العافية.
Mukhtar, may God give you health.
أهليين أهلاً أستاذي أهلاً وسهلاً شرفتم.
Welcome, welcome my teacher, welcome, you have honored us.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيكم ببرنامجكم أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome to you in your program, welcome.
الله يسلمكم.
May God keep you safe.
هلا تحكي لي إيمت تشكلت هالضيعة بشكلها الحالي؟
Now, could you tell me when this village was formed in its
current state?
الضيعة تشكلت...
The village was formed...
Arabic
It was formed about 120, 130 years to 150 years ago, for
example.
Arabic
The houses were all made of mud, I mean mud blocks.
And they used to bring straw from outside and put pillars
for it and put straw on it, it was all dirt.
Arabic
Considering the farmers, so that they wouldn't keep going to
Sholaqan and coming back, they stayed here.
Arabic
And the farmer used to work all year round.
Because of the road, so they wouldn't get tired on the road,
they built here and stayed here and it became...
Arabic
Of course, they were sharecroppers, they used to work for a
quarter of the yield.
Arabic
Yes, sharecroppers.
Sharecroppers, yes, they worked here as sharecroppers.
Arabic
So originally, this village was the property of the Sido
Mimo family from Sholaqan?
Arabic
The village's ownership is like any other village, among 14
villages belonging to Khalil Agha Sido Mimo.
Arabic
Okay, okay. And they were farmers here, when they first
built, they built mud houses, they lived in them and worked
the lands.
Arabic
Yes, they built stables for horses, yes for horses, for
animals, everything was ready.
Arabic
So they wouldn't go, I mean get tired on the road going and
coming, they stayed here, they lived here.
Arabic
And bit by bit it was built up, developed, and became a
village.
Arabic
Who was it administratively under at that time?
The village? The lands were lands belonging to Khalil Agha
of Sholaqan.
Arabic
Ah, afterwards it came under Jindires.
When it became a village with its own independence, it came
under Jindires.
Arabic
Yes, it is under, yes indeed, our village is under Jindires,
yes, under Jindires.
Arabic
Now what I understood is that this village was also
approximately located on the Silk Road.
Arabic
And it had, like, rest stops, khans...
Khans, yes. It had a khan here at the main road, the
beginning of the main road.
Arabic
On the Afrin - Jindires road there was a khan, and the khan
belonged to Khalil Agha Sido Mimo.
Arabic
The Silk Road, when they used to come, there was something
like a rest stop here.
Arabic
Or exchanging trade, commercial exchange among them.
They slept here, there were stables, there was like a hotel,
you know, they slept in it.
Arabic
Commercial shops.
Commercial shops, they exchanged trade in them, whoever is
continuing to Kilis, and whoever is continuing to Aleppo.
Arabic
There is something I must ask you about, now this village is
called Sheikh Abdul Rahman village.
Arabic
And it has a shrine called the Sheikh Abdul Rahman Shrine.
We want to know about this shrine and go see it now.
Arabic
And we also want to, I know there is a bridge.
There is an old bridge.
Arabic
An old bridge under which the water of the Sheikh Abdul
Rahman River passes.
Arabic
Water, yes, the Sheikh Abdul Rahman River.
Which consists of a group of springs that feed this
watercourse.
Arabic
Yes, they gather and become a river and it goes to the Afrin
River, it flows into the Afrin River, yes.
Arabic
Alright, let's go now to the ziyarah (shrine) as you call
it, or the Sheikh Abdul Rahman Shrine.
Arabic
Please go ahead, welcome, a hundred greetings, please.
As you can see now, we are heading towards the shrine area.
Arabic
Which is a sanctuary, a tomb, or a mausoleum of a righteous
man.
Arabic
It's appearing to us at the far end of the screen, at the
end of the screen the area is appearing to us.
Arabic
The village, as we can see, is very beautiful.
More than 95% of its area, the area of its agricultural
lands, is planted with olive trees.
Arabic
I mean, it is surrounded by olives from all four sides.
As you can see, we have now reached the shrine.
Arabic
A beautiful area, and it is on the course of the Sheikh
Abdul Rahman River.
Arabic
Which is named, I mean, the Sheikh Abdul Rahman Shrine.
And it is located on the edge of the riverbed, surrounded by
trees, very beautiful.
Arabic
Let's get down, Mukhtar.
Please go ahead.
Arabic
Now Mukhtar, as we can observe, the area has a touristic
dimension.
Arabic
Yes.
Isn't that right?
Arabic
Yes.
Now there is a spring here, where is the spring that feeds
this riverbed of the Sheikh?
Arabic
Several springs, not just one, several springs but a little
further up.
Arabic
After the shrine, there are several springs that come and
flow into each other and form a riverbed.
Arabic
And it passes through the village of Sheikh Abdul Rahman,
Tal Hamou, Frieriyeh, and flows into the Afrin River.
Arabic
I know there is a spring next to the shrine?
There is an old one here.
Arabic
Let's see it, where is it?
This way, this is it.
Arabic
But it seems that currently there is someone here near the
shrine.
Arabic
He closed it because of the dirt, you know, because kids
come here to play and throw dirt and stuff in it.
Arabic
So now he closed it and put a hose on it, and clear water is
coming out of it, and like that it pours into the gallon.
Arabic
Whoever needs it comes and takes from it.
Alright, now this lovely, beautiful house which is, I mean,
surrounded by a very nice garden of these trees, what is
this house?
Arabic
This is the shrine servant's house. The shrine servant was
from the Haidar family, Sheikh Haidar.
Arabic
And then after him was Sheikh Abdul Rahman, and then lastly
Sheikh Muhammad was the shrine servant.
Arabic
This house is very beautiful.
Very, very much.
Arabic
I mean, it is very old, these palm trees, wow.
Now Mukhtar, we have reached the shrine, let's go in,
please.
Arabic
Please.
Wow, what a magnificent and beautiful tree!
Arabic
A very large tree, its age is maybe, from what I know, 150 -
200 years.
Arabic
People used to come and gather here under it in the summer.
Weddings... the Sheikhs would come here, the family of, for
example, Al-Haidar, the Kilani family, the family of I don't
know who.
Arabic
They would hold gatherings here.
Let's just stop here for a bit and see, come here Mukhtar,
this is a mulberry tree, isn't it?
Arabic
This is a mulberry tree, yes.
But it seems its trunk is almost hollow?
Arabic
Its trunk is hollow, due to its old age it became hollow
from the inside, and now it has started to sprout all over
again.
Arabic
And they cut it a while ago so it would sprout again and
provide shade inside the courtyard, this is the shrine's
courtyard.
Arabic
People come and sit here, they come, you know, for
childbirth, people if they don't have anyone.
Arabic
They make a vow, you mean?
Yes, if someone vowed something, for example, having a girl
or a boy, they also come and sacrifice an animal here.
Arabic
Were there specific religious ceremonies here, Sufi sheikhs?
A lot, a lot, a lot, a lot used to be here, Sufi sheikhs.
Arabic
The trunk's age, I mean its width is about three meters
roughly.
Arabic
Yes, by God, even more, if we brought four or five men and
we wrapped around it, I don't think it would be enough for
it.
Arabic
Its circumference inside the shrine. Of course, this is
another mulberry tree.
Arabic
This is another mulberry tree too, yes.
But it seems slightly younger in age.
Arabic
Yes, by God, that one is older, the one I remember was
older, this one came later, I mean.
Arabic
And they took care of it and it got, what's it called, they
watered it and stuff, and it did well, this is the shrine.
Arabic
And this one is, what's it called?
Here it is written renewed in the year 65, meaning 1965.
Arabic
Yes, this was renewed for the year 65.
Please enter.
Arabic
Please, let's open the door.
Go ahead, sir. Mukhtar, it seems this is a mosque.
Arabic
A mosque, and there is the shrine.
This is the mosque's courtyard here, and there is a shrine
inside here, it has a private room, the shrine.
Arabic
Let's see it, please.
Now this tomb here, which is the shrine.
Arabic
Yes. Yes, this is it.
Now it's written here, written here is the Mosque of the
Great Companion Abdul Rahman bin Auf.
Arabic
Let's stand here, Abdul Rahman bin Auf, yes.
Abdul Rahman bin Auf, is there any relationship between the
great companion Abdul Rahman bin Auf, may God be pleased
with him, and this grave?
Arabic
Is it his grave or whose grave?
No, this is not his grave, his grave from what I heard from
the pilgrims who go to Hajj and come back, they say his
grave is in Al-Baqi'.
Arabic
In Al-Baqi', but this, people say he visited, meaning a
shrine he visited here, people say he was wounded here,
people say he rested here.
Arabic
So there are many stories.
Meaning that he passed by here. He had a passing through
here.
Arabic
Yes, he had a passing through here.
And they considered the place of his passing as a shrine,
but whose grave is this?
Arabic
This is a grave, a coffin, I mean supposedly for him, I mean
supposedly they made it as a symbol, as if it was for him,
but no, it is not his.
Arabic
Alright, let's continue and see the location of the
riverbed, and go to the bridge afterwards.
Arabic
Alright, please, welcome.
Now this is the Sheikh Abdul Rahman River, a group of
springs near the shrine flowing into this valley, let's call
it.
Arabic
And it penetrates the Sheikh Abdul Rahman village and flows
into Frieriyeh and goes to the Afrin River.
Arabic
Exactly.
It seems, it seems here, why is the water black?
Arabic
The water is black because after the shrine there is a
village called Faqiran, which has an olive press.
Arabic
And the press discharges its water, the press's water into
the river, so because of this the color of the water
changed.
Arabic
Now does this watercourse remain in summer and winter?
Yes, summer and winter it's there, yes, but in winter it
becomes, I mean, strong, in summer in the eighth and ninth
months it lessens a bit.
Arabic
This surrounds Sheikh Abdul Rahman, the village of Sheikh
Abdul Rahman from the northern and western sides.
Arabic
Right, it comes, it comes from the north, because there are
several springs.
Arabic
A spring gathers with a spring and it becomes...
سيل بتجي على... هاد بتجي من شمال غربي الزيارة المزار
The torrent comes to... this comes from the northwest of Al-
Ziyara, the shrine,
وبتعدي على قرية شيخ عبد الرحمن على تل حمو على فريريه وبتصب
بنهر عفرين.
and passes through the village of Sheikh Abdul Rahman, to
Tel Hammo, to Feryriyeh, and pours into the Afrin River.
تمام. هلا رح نروح، في عنا نروح على الجسر؟
Okay. Now we will go, do we have a bridge to go to?
ايه في جسر، نعم.
Yes, there is a bridge, yes.
شرف.
Please, go ahead.
تفضلوا أهلا وسهلا.
Go ahead, welcome.
هون نحنا بنهاية الضيعة والمجرى صاير على غربي الضيعة، بمحاذاة
القرية مباشرة.
Here we are at the end of the village and the stream is on
the west of the village, directly adjacent to the village.
مجرى نهر عفرين شيخ عبد الرحمن؟
The stream of the river from Sheikh Abdul Rahman?
مجرى النهر اللي جاي من شيخ عبد الرحمن من الزيارة
The stream of the river coming from Sheikh Abdul Rahman,
from Al-Ziyara,
وبتعدي عنا من الضيعة وبتصب بتل حمو وفريريه وبتصب بنهر عفرين.
and it passes by us from the village and pours into Tel
Hammo and Feryriyeh, and pours into the Afrin River.
هي هاد المجرى مبين واضح وهي الضيعة موجودة.
This is the stream, it's clearly visible, and here is the
village.
وبيجي هون، هاد الجسر القديم.
And it comes here, this is the old bridge.
هاد الجسر القديم؟
This is the old bridge?
هاد الجسر القديم اللي صار له أيام فرنسا، بيقولوا الفرنسيين
هنن عمروا.
This is the old bridge that has been here since the days of
France, they say the French built it.
باعتبار كان عالزمان الأولي المي كتير، السيل كتير.
Because in the old days there was a lot of water, a lot of
torrents.
مشان سير الحركة حطوا هالجسر هاد أيام الفرنسيين.
To keep traffic moving, they put this bridge up during the
French days.
ومشان يمروا من فوقه ويروحوا ويجوا.
So they could pass over it and go back and forth.
هلا أنا حسب ما فهمت انه هاد جسر...
Now, as I understand it, that this bridge...
اللي هو قريب جدا من طريق عفرين جنديرس كان يمر من فوقه
الطريق.
which is very close to the Afrin-Jindires road, the road
used to pass over it.
ايه ع الطريق الرئيسي.
Yes, on the main road.
بشكل كوع، لفة.
In the shape of an elbow, a curve.
بشكل كوع ولفة، بعدين عملوا له تحويلة مشان ما... لأن كانت
تصير حوادث.
In the shape of an elbow and a curve, then they made a
bypass for it so that... because accidents used to happen.
هي صايرة كوع وتصير حوادث، بعدين عملوا له فكرة أخدوا الطريق
ساوي وراحوا.
It was a curve and accidents happened, then they came up
with an idea, took the road straight and left.
دعموا الجسر لانه هاد كان يصير فوقه الطريق الرئيسي.
They reinforced the bridge because the main road used to go
over it.
بالضبط، تدعيم الجسر في عمود وما زالت موجودة.
Exactly, reinforcing the bridge, there is a pillar and it is
still there.
بس التانية راحت نتيجة السيول اللي عم تجينا.
But the other one is gone due to the torrents that come to
us.
تجينا سيول من فقيران، من كوركان، من خرزان، من چولاقان، من كل
الضيع اللي فوق.
Torrents come to us from Faqiran, from Kurkan, from Kharzan,
from Cholakan, from all the villages up there.
تتجمع وقت تصير مطر بغزارة...
They gather when it rains heavily...
صدقني أنا ياما شفته، الوادي هاد ملاته يجي مي.
Believe me, I have often seen it, this whole valley gets
filled with water.
هلا كان في طاحونة مائية كمان؟
Now, was there a water mill too?
طاحونة مائية بالزيارة... بالزيارة كانت تشتغل ع المي.
A water mill in Al-Ziyara... in Al-Ziyara it used to work on
water.
ع المي.
On water.
ايه، طاحونة نظامية كانت تشتغل ع المي.
Yes, a proper mill that worked on water.
تمام. هاد هو الجسر.
Okay. This is the bridge.
هاد هو الجسر.
This is the bridge.
طيب الله يعطيك العافية يا مختار. شكرا لك.
Alright, God give you health, Mukhtar. Thank you.
أهلين الله يسلمكم وكل الشكر... أهلين سهلين بالتوفيق ان شاء
الله.
Welcome, God keep you safe, and all thanks... Welcome, good
luck God willing.
يمكن اختصار الحياة الاقتصادية ومصدر الدخل لأهالي القرية
والنازحين فيها بالزيتون.
The economic life and source of income for the people of the
village and the displaced people in it can be summarized by
olives.
مساحة لا تقل عن 95% من مساحة القرية مزروعة بالزيتون...
An area of no less than 95% of the village's area is planted
with olives...
يعمل فيها أهالي القرية والنازحين إليها.
where the village's residents and the displaced people work.
في هذه الفقرة سنكون معكم في جولة داخل بساتين القرية...
In this segment, we will be with you on a tour inside the
village's orchards...
لنلتقي بأصحابها والعمال الذين يعملون في هذا الموسم.
to meet their owners and the workers working in this season.
وأيضاً سندخل إلى إحدى معاصر الزيتون في القرية لنتعرف على
أوضاع الموسم فيها. تابعونا.
And we will also enter one of the olive presses in the
village to learn about the season's conditions there. Follow
us.
ما شاء الله.
Mashallah.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته.
And upon you be peace, and God's mercy and blessings.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
ع البركة.
Blessings upon your work.
حياك الله ع البركة.
God greet you, blessings.
كأنه قربتوا تخلصوا؟
It seems you are almost finished?
اي والله يعني على وشك.
Yes, by God, we are about to.
أهلا... وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله.
Welcome... and upon you be peace and God's mercy.
شلونكم؟
How are you?
الحمد لله، الله يعافيك.
Praise be to God, God give you health.
شلون الموسم؟
How is the season?
والله الحمد لله.
By God, praise be to God.
كويس؟
Is it good?
كويس الحمد لله.
Good, praise be to God.
اشو نوع هالزيتون؟
What type of olive is this?
والله مو انه يعني الحامل حامل، يعني وسط.
By God, it's not like the fruitful one is fully loaded, I
mean it's average.
وسط، بس اشو نوعه؟
Average, but what is its type?
زيتي هاد.
This is oil-producing (Zeiti).
زيتي هاد. أنا شفت هون تحت شوي...
This is oil-producing. I saw here down a bit...
شفت تحت هي الشجرة كتير هرر، يعني هاد عطون ولا زيتون؟
I saw under this tree a lot of fallen ones, I mean is this
for pickling (Atoun) or olives?
هاد الزيتون وقت المطر هر وانطب تحت الارض.
These olives fell during the rain and dropped on the ground.
ايوا، صار تحت الشجر.
I see, it went under the trees.
وهلا يعني بصير متل العطون والفوقاني زيتون.
And now it becomes like pickling olives (Atoun) and the ones
above are regular olives.
هاد هاد بصير عطون؟
This... this becomes pickling olives?
ايوا.
Yes.
وهاد ما بيصير عصر زيت؟
And this can't be pressed for oil?
بيصير، شلون ما بيصير.
It can, why wouldn't it?
بيصير.
It can.
القطاف ان شاء الله صاير كويس، عم تتعبوا؟
The picking is going well God willing, are you getting
tired?
والله لك شلون ما بدنا نتعب.
By God, how could we not get tired.
في تعب، من ايمت عم تيجوا لهون؟
There is fatigue. Since when do you come here?
من غدين.
Since early morning.
لا لا، اقصد من اي ساعة عم تجوا لهون على...
No, no, I mean from what time do you come here to...
من الساعة 7 الصبح.
From 7 in the morning.
7، وهلا تقريبا صارت الساعة 5.
7, and now it's almost 5 o'clock.
ايوا.
Yes.
شقد موسمكم هون بيطول؟ انتو عمال...
How long does your season last here? You are workers...
عمال ايه.
Workers, yes.
عمال. شقد موسمكم هون بيطول يعني كم شهر؟
Workers. How long does your season last here, I mean how
many months?
يعني من الشهر وتحت.
I mean from a month and under.
شهر وتحت، شقد بتطالعوا؟
A month and under, how much do you produce?
بنطالع يعني حوالي الـ 10، 15، 20 تنكة.
We produce, I mean, about 10, 15, 20 tins.
العيلة الك الواحد؟
The family, for you alone?
لا العيلة، العامل يعني بيشيل له تنكة ونص، تنكتين.
No, the family. The worker, I mean, gets a tin and a half,
two tins.
بالشهر؟
In a month?
الشهر.
The month.
الله يرزقكم يا رب، الله يرزقكم يا رب.
May God provide for you, O Lord. May God provide for you, O
Lord.
ايش لون يعني احكيلي عن هيك بعض يعني يومياتكم اش بتسووا فيها
غير انه مثلا بتهروا زيتون؟
How... I mean, tell me about some of your daily activities,
what do you do besides, for example, knocking down olives?
شلون بتشتروا؟ كيف بتقضوا نهاركم؟
How do you buy things? How do you spend your day?
بترتاحوا شوي؟ بتغنوا؟ تاكلوا وتشربوا؟
Do you rest a bit? Do you sing? Eat and drink?
والله بناكل ونشرب ونغني 24 ساعة والحياة بدها تمشي.
By God, we eat, drink, and sing 24 hours, and life must go
on.
ساكنين بخيمة ولا ساكنين بـ...
Do you live in a tent or do you live in...
لا، بخيم هون.
No, in tents here.
بخيم. شو بتغنوا؟
In tents. What do you sing?
والله حسب اللي بيجي بالبال.
By God, whatever comes to mind.
سمعني لشوف هيك شغلة صغيرة قبل ما امشي.
Let me hear a little something before I go.
يقول أبدت علي بمبسم به زواويل وبمفرق القذلة سوات الهلالي
He says, she appeared to me with a smile that has beauty
marks, and with a parting of hair like the crescent moon.
يقول استغفري ربك يا بنت عن قولي اني عبد من عبيد الموالي
He says, ask your Lord for forgiveness, girl, for my saying
that I am a slave among the loyal slaves.
حنا عبيد الرب سيد المخاليق وان ما جرى يا بنت هذي احوالي
We are the slaves of the Lord, the Master of creations, and
whatever happens, girl, these are my conditions.
الله الله الله ها! هاد الجود. الله يعطيكم العافية.
Allah, Allah, Allah, ha! This is generosity. God give you
health.
الله يعافيك.
God give you health.
عفتكم بالعافية يا رب، نهاركم سعيد ان شاء الله.
I leave you in good health, O Lord. Have a happy day, God
willing.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
سلام ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace and God's mercy and blessings.
الله يعطيك العافية.
God give you health.
أهلا وسهلا، مية السلامة.
Welcome, a hundred greetings.
وين كنتوا هيك؟
Where were you?
والله كنا نحوش زيتون.
By God, we were harvesting olives.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
منين حضرتك؟
Where are you from?
ريف حلب الجنوبي.
Southern countryside of Aleppo.
أهلا وسهلا فيك والصبايا والشباب؟
Welcome. And the girls and guys?
كلهم ريف حلب الجنوبي.
All of them are from the southern countryside of Aleppo.
احكيلي شلون عم تشتغلوا هون اليوم حواش الزيتون، يعني شقد
بتاخدوا؟
Tell me how you are working here today harvesting olives, I
mean how much do you get?
والله نحن نشتغل هين بالزيتون ناخد سبعة والثامن.
By God, we work here in the olives, we take seven and the
eighth.
يعني سبعة للمعلم وثمانية النا.
I mean seven for the boss and the eighth is ours.
سبع شوالات يعني؟
Seven sacks, you mean?
سبع شوالات للمعلم وشوال النا.
Seven sacks for the boss and a sack for us.
ان شاء الله وضعكم مليح؟
God willing, your situation is good?
الحمد لله رب العالمين مستورة.
Praise be to God, Lord of the Worlds, it's covered (okay).
انتو ساكنين بالشيخ عبد الرحمن؟
Do you live in Sheikh Abdul Rahman?
احنا ساكنين عند الاغا، الشيخ... عند الشيخ عبد الرحمن.
We live at the Agha's, Sheikh... at Sheikh Abdul Rahman.
هون ساكنين يعني؟
You live here, then?
ايه نعم.
Yes, indeed.
تمام. شلون الموسم السنة؟
Okay. How is the season this year?
والله الحمد لله ماشية الامور.
By God, praise be to God, things are moving.
يعني مو هالكل واجد يعني بس ماشي الحال.
I mean, not extremely abundant, but it's okay.
نسيت أسألك ساكنين بخيم متل هون ولا ساكنين ببيوت؟
I forgot to ask you, do you live in tents like here or do
you live in houses?
لا احنا ساكنين ببيت.
No, we live in a house.
ببيت. الله يقويكم يا رب، الله يعطيكم العافية.
In a house. May God give you strength, O Lord. God give you
health.
الله يسلمك.
God keep you safe.
مية السلامة فيكم، مع السلامة.
A hundred greetings to you. Goodbye.
الله يسلمك.
God keep you safe.
ع البركة.
Blessings upon your work.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
God give you health.
المعلم هون؟
Is the boss here?
تفضل يا هلا، أهلا وسهلا.
Go ahead, welcome, welcome.
الله يرزقكم يا شباب.
May God provide for you, guys.
الله يسلمك ويحفظك.
God keep you safe and protect you.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله، أهلا وسهلا.
And upon you be peace and God's mercy, welcome.
مرحبا عمو.
Hello, uncle.
أهلين يا مرحبا، يا هلا وسهلا.
Welcome, hello, welcome.
حياكم الله.
God greet you.
أهلين فيك.
Welcome to you.
عمي حضرتك صاحب المعصرة؟
Uncle, are you the owner of the press?
الملك لله تعالى، الحمد لله.
Ownership belongs to God Almighty, praise be to God.
نحكي شوي عن هالمعصرة شرف.
Let's talk a little about this press, if you please.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
نتعرف عليك؟
Can we get to know you?
حسن حمادة.
Hassan Hamadeh.
يا أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
صاحب المعصرة.
The owner of the press.
يا أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
احكيلي ع موسم السنة، شلون موسم السنة؟
Tell me about the season this year, how is the season this
year?
الموسم مقبول، بس بدينا بكير.
The season is acceptable, but we started early.
يعني... العالم حوشت بكير يعني ما استنوا لحتى يكمل الزيتون،
I mean... people harvested early, I mean they didn't wait
for the olives to fully mature,
وماشي الحال والحمد لله رب العالمين.
but things are fine, and praise be to God, Lord of the
Worlds.
الحمد لله، كأنه في عندكم زحمة؟
Praise be to God. It seems you have a crowd?
نعم؟
Yes?
في عندكم زحمة؟
Do you have a crowd?
انا شايف والله هي الشوالات الحمد لله.
I see, by God, these sacks, praise be to God.
شقد صارلكم بديانين؟ فاتحين؟
How long has it been since you started? Opened?
شي 27 يوم.
About 27 days.
27 يوم، يمكن اقل كمان.
27 days, maybe less too.
لايمت بتتوقعوا تستمروا؟
Until when do you expect to continue?
لبين ما يخلص الزيتون.
Until the olives are finished.
يعني شهر شهر وشوي؟
I mean a month, a month and a bit?
لا ما في هالشي هاد، الله يطرح البركة.
No, not that much, may God bring blessings.
امين يا رب.
Amen, O Lord.
بس الموسم تقريبا بقي ربعه، 25% او ما بقي.
But the season, almost a quarter of it is left, 25%, or
maybe less.
سيدي الله يعين.
Sir, may God help.
الله يحفظكم.
May God protect you.
شلون نسبة القطع؟
How is the yield percentage?
القطع لانه الزيتون عجر مو مكتمل.
The yield, because the olives are unripe, not fully
mature...
ايه ما هو كتير يعني ما هو كويس؟
Yes, it's not a lot, I mean it's not good?
لا ما هو كويس.
No, it's not good.
ايش هو نوع الزيت في الضيعة هون؟
What is the type of oil in the village here?
الزيت عندنا كله شخوطة.
The oil we have is all Shkhouta.
ايش هو يعني كله شخوطة؟
What does it mean all Shkhouta?
يعني خمس شخوطة ست شخوطة.
I mean five Shkhouta, six Shkhouta.
ايه شو نوعه يعني هون كويس؟ مستواه جيد؟ شو؟
Yes, what type is it, I mean is it good here? Its level is
good? What?
هون زيتنا معروف زيت الكردي منطقة عفرين زيت معروف يعني.
Here our oil is known, Kurdish oil, Afrin region, it's a
known oil.
ممتاز.
Excellent.
ممتاز وجيد جدا.
Excellent and very good.
ما شاء الله، ونوعه الزيتون شو نوعه هاد اللي هون بالضيعة؟
Mashallah, and its type, the olives, what type is it here in
the village?
هاد عنا زيتونا زيتي.
This, we have oil-producing olives (Zeiti).
غير الخلخالي او المعراوي او الصوراني، ما في عنا نحن هون، كله
زيتي زيتي، كله زيتي نعم.
Other than Khalkhali or Ma'arawi or Sourani, we don't have
those here, it's all Zeiti Zeiti, all Zeiti, yes.
هلا هاد بتخمروه هون ولا بتتركوه...
Now, do you ferment it here or do you leave it...
لا لا لا اول يوم تاني يوم بالصب.
No, no, no, the first day, the second day, it gets poured.
ما بيتم.
It doesn't stay.
أولي كانوا يتركوه، يتخمر يتركوه.
Originally they used to leave it, ferment it, leave it.
أولي كان تغيرت الامور كلها.
Originally, it was... things have all changed.
تغيرت مو هيك؟
Changed, right?
ايه.
Yes.
ندخل شوي ع المعصرة؟
Shall we go inside the press a bit?
شرف.
Go ahead.
هون شو هون؟
What's here, what's here?
هذا الورق، بيطلع لبرا.
This is the leaves, they go outside.
الغسالة بتغسل الزيتون، بعد ما ينغسل...
The washing machine washes the olives. After it gets
washed...
هون مي سخنة مو هيك؟
Here is hot water, right?
مي صافية... باردة.
Clear water... cold.
باردة؟
Cold?
لا لا لا، لا لا لا.
No, no, no. No, no, no.
مي باردة، بتيجي بعدين من هون وهيك بتصير مي سخنة.
Cold water, then it comes from here and so on, it becomes
hot water.
نمشي هيك شوي.
Let's walk this way a bit.
هون مكابس؟ مكابس مكابس.
Here are presses? Presses, presses.
طيب تفضل عمو شوي شوي.
Okay, go ahead uncle, slowly, slowly.
هي العجانات.
These are the mixers (malaxers).
هي العجانة؟
This is the mixer?
ايه هي بتخلط العجانة.
Yes, this mixer mixes.
الزمم بنحط الاسامي.
The batches, we put the names.
هي الذمة.
This is the batch.
هي الذمة، ننتقل هي الذمة التانية، هي الذمة التالتة.
This is the batch, we move to the second batch, this is the
third batch.
شقد بيطول هون؟
How long does it take here?
حسب، يعني تلات ارباع ساعة، ساعة، بتطول.
It depends, I mean three-quarters of an hour, an hour, it
takes.
هون مي سخنة؟
Is there hot water here?
هون مي سخنة، ايه مي سخنة هون.
Here is hot water, yes hot water here.
وين بيطلع الزيت؟
Where does the oil come out?
هون ع العجان هون، هاد اسمه ديكانتر.
Here to the mixer here, this is called a decanter.
هي مية السودا، وهي الزيت لحالها يجي.
This is the black water, and this is the oil coming alone.
هاد الزيت.
This is the oil.
وين بروح؟ بيصفي وين هون؟
Where does it go? Does it filter where, here?
بيجي ع الفرازة.
It comes to the separator.
هاد الفرازة، هي للزيت.
This separator, this is for the oil.
هون، اذا صار تهريب زيت، بيجي لهون، بيرجع بينسحب بيرجع ع
الفرازة.
Here, if there is an oil leak, it comes here, gets pulled
back, and goes back to the separator.
لا بتدفع لك تنكة زيت بترجع قد تنكتين.
No, you pay a tin of oil, it returns as much as two tins.
ما شاء الله لون الزيت كثير حلو.
Mashallah, the color of the oil is very beautiful.
إي، نحن ما بناخذ مصاري.
Yes, we don't take money.
شغلة، بسألك ياها، جرب.
A thing I'll ask you, try.
ما شاء الله تنك زيت كثير.
Mashallah, there are many tins of oil.
إي.
Yes.
شقد بتعبي تنكة؟
How much does a tin fill?
من 16 دولار وتحت.
From 16 dollars and below.
تحت.
Below.
احكي لي عن عاداتكم هون أثناء موسم الزيتون، موسم الزيت، عصر
الزيت، إيش بيصير؟
Tell me about your customs here during the olive season, the
oil season, pressing the oil, what happens?
هو يعني بيكون مثل عرس، موسم.
It's, I mean, it's like a wedding, a season.
إي.
Yes.
والعالم بتطالع رزقاتها وبتلمه.
And people bring out their livelihoods and gather them.
إي.
Yes.
وبسددوا ديونهم وكذا هاللي عليهم يعني.
And they pay off their debts and whatever they owe, you
know.
شلون بيحتفلوا فيه؟
How do they celebrate it?
نعم؟
Yes?
شلون بيحتفلوا بهالموسم باعتبار مثل يعني...
How do they celebrate this season, considering it's like...
يعني موسم، يعني وقت بيكون واحد عنده موسم بده يحتفلوا يعني.
I mean, a season, I mean, when someone has a season, they
want to celebrate, you know.
بيحتفلوا يعني، بيساووا ذبائح مثلاً؟
They celebrate, I mean, do they slaughter sacrifices, for
example?
لا بيجوا بيلموا زيتونهم كذا بيعصروهم.
No, they come, gather their olives, and so on, and press
them.
بالمعصرة إيش بيصير هون؟ ما بيغنوا؟ ما بيفرحوا؟ ما بياكلوا؟
At the press, what happens here? Don't they sing? Don't they
rejoice? Don't they eat?
بعدين بيفرحوا وبيكسحوا...
Afterwards, they rejoice and prune...
أنا بعرف...
I know...
إنه بيستنوا الموسم...
That they wait for the season...
ليزوجوا الأولاد.
To marry off the children.
أكيد بدهم يغطوا بعدين مصاريفهم يعني...
Sure, they want to cover their expenses afterwards, you
know...
من الموسم.
From the season.
عليهم ديون، عليهم فلاحة، عليهم كساحة، عليهم التزامات معيشة
وكذا...
They have debts, they have plowing, they have pruning, they
have living commitments, and so on...
الله يعطيك العافية عمي أبو حسن.
May God give you health, Uncle Abu Hassan.
مبروك، نحن مضيفينكم قهوة.
Congratulations, we are serving you coffee.
الله يرزقك.
May God provide for you.
نحن مضيفينكم قهوة.
We are serving you coffee.
إي والله. شربت.
Yes, indeed. I drank.
شربت، بالهنا.
You drank, to your health.
[Musiq]
[Music]
بآخر فقرة من هالجولة ومع الغروب...
In the last segment of this tour, and with the sunset...
تقريباً رح نكون بزيارة لبيت العم أبو محمد...
Almost, we will be visiting the house of Uncle Abu
Muhammad...
اللي هو من أهالي هالضيعة الحلوة والبسيطة.
Who is from the people of this beautiful and simple village.
بيته كمان بيتميز بالبساطة والجمال...
His house is also characterized by simplicity and beauty...
أرض ديار واسعة ومزروعة أشجار مختلفة.
A spacious courtyard planted with various trees.
مظلة وورد ورياحين ما شاء الله.
A canopy, roses, and basil, Mashallah.
حسب ما فهمت إنه هو يعني مصاب...
As I understood, he is, you know, injured...
أصيب بحادث بالأيام الأخيرة.
He was injured in an accident in recent days.
لنطمن عليه ونتعرف على عيلته البسيطة ونختم معكم.
Let's check on him, get to know his simple family, and
conclude with you.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته.
And upon you be peace, and the mercy of God and His
blessings.
يعطيك العافية قبل كل شي.
May God give you health before everything.
الله يعافيك يا رب.
May God give you health, O Lord.
شلونك عمي أبو محمد؟
How are you, Uncle Abu Muhammad?
شلونك؟
How are you?
ليش عم تبكي؟ مرحبا أم محمد.
Why are you crying? Hello, Umm Muhammad.
أهلين وسهلين، سلامات، الحمد لله.
Welcome, greetings, thank God.
شوبك؟ سلامتك.
What's wrong? Get well soon.
والله بتجيني البكية هيك.
I swear, the tears just come to me like this.
سلامتك.
Get well soon.
شو صاير معك؟ طمنيني عنكم. شلونك؟
What happened to you? Reassure me about you. How are you?
الحمد لله، الحمد لله.
Thank God, thank God.
صرت أحسن إن شاء الله؟
You've become better, God willing?
الحمد لله.
Thank God.
الحمد لله. شلونك خالة أم محمد؟
Thank God. How are you, Aunt Umm Muhammad?
الحمد لله رب العالمين.
Praise be to God, Lord of the Worlds.
الحمد لله. احكي لي عن هيك عيلتكم الحلوة عن بيتكم... احكي لي.
Thank God. Tell me about your beautiful family, about your
house... tell me.
الحمد لله، يعني عيلتي، بيتي، ولا العيلة كلها؟
Thank God. You mean my family, my house, or the whole
family?
عيلتك، عيلتك إنت، بيتك.
Your family, your own family, your house.
الحمد لله، عيلة نحن بسيطة، كنا عايشين وولادي درسوا الحمد
لله.
Thank God, we are a simple family, we were living and my
children studied, thank God.
بهالوضع هذا وهالأزمة هاي، تأزمت هيك ونزحنا وولادي كلهم
سافروا لبرا.
In this situation and this crisis, things got complicated,
we were displaced, and all my children traveled abroad.
هذا سبب بكاء أبو محمد؟
Is this the reason for Abu Muhammad's crying?
بكاء أبو محمد، زلمة كبير، قلبه رقيق، وهيك صاير حنون زيادة.
Abu Muhammad's crying... he is an old man, his heart is
tender, and he has become overly affectionate.
سلامتك. إن شاء الله رح يشوفوك عالتلفزيون وإن شاء الله
بيطمنوا عليك...
Get well soon. God willing, they will see you on television,
and God willing, they will be reassured about you...
وإنت بتطمن عليهم بإذن الله تعالى.
And you will be reassured about them, God willing.
إن شاء الله، إن شاء الله. يا رب.
God willing, God willing. O Lord.
كم ولد عندكم؟
How many children do you have?
ستة.
Six.
الله يخليهم شباب وصبايا؟
May God keep them. Young men and women?
أربع بنات وشابين.
Four daughters and two young men.
إيش عم يدرسوا؟ إيش تتجوزوا؟ احكي لي عنهم هيك شوي.
What are they studying? Did they get married? Tell me a bit
about them.
والله أول وحدة درست للسابع وتجوزت.
Well, the first one studied until the seventh grade and got
married.
ووحدة أخذت بكالوريا وتجوزت.
And one got her baccalaureate and got married.
والثانية كمان، تاريخ ثاني سنة جامعة كمان...
And the other one too, history, second year of university
too...
صار هالوضع هذا كمان ما قدرت تكمل.
This situation happened, and she couldn't continue either.
كمان هي تجوزت.
She also got married.
وآخر وحدة كمان الصغيرة...
And the last one too, the youngest...
كمان هي صف الثامن كانت...
She was also in the eighth grade...
وما حاولت يعني تكمل، كمان هي صار لها سنة كمان متجوزة.
And she didn't try to continue, she has also been married
for a year.
الله يديمكم فوق راسهم جميعا يا رب.
May God keep you above their heads always, O Lord.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
والشباب كمان، واحد كمان سجل أول سنة أدب إنجليزي جامعة كمان
ما قدر يداوم.
And the young men too, one registered for his first year of
English literature at the university, and he also couldn't
attend.
وواحد كمان دخل صناعة كمان ما داوم، بهالنزوح هذا وهالوضع صار
وسافروا.
And another one also entered a vocational school, and he
didn't attend either, with this displacement and this
situation that happened, and they traveled.
الله يجمعكم فيهم يا رب.
May God reunite you with them, O Lord.
عمي أبو محمد، فيك تحكي لي شوي يعني عن أهل هالضيعة، طباعهم،
عاداتهم الحلوة، الكريمة؟
Uncle Abu Muhammad, can you tell me a little bit about the
people of this village, their nature, their beautiful,
generous customs?
ما فيني أحكي.
I can't talk.
ما فيك؟
You can't?
ما فيني أحكي.
I can't talk.
سلامتك. مقدر ظرفك. فيك تحكي إنت؟
Get well soon. I appreciate your situation. Can you talk?
احكي لي شوي هيك عن أهل هالضيعة الطيبين.
Tell me a little bit about the good people of this village.
والله أهل الضيعة كلهم كويسين وفلاحين والجماعة متواضعين
كويسين يعني...
Well, the people of the village are all good and farmers,
and they are a humble, good group, you know...
يعني لبعضهم الحمد لله وقت المناسبات كلهم بيجتمعوا مع
بعضهم...
I mean, for each other, thank God, during occasions they all
gather together...
بيساعدوا بعضهم بيوقفوا جنب بعضهم...
They help each other, they stand by each other...
الحمد لله متفقين يعني كويسين.
Thank God, they are in agreement, you know, they are good.
الحمد لله. متعايشين مع بعض وبحبوا بعض.
Thank God. They coexist and love each other.
نعم.
Yes.
أنا لاحظت إنه كل بيوت الضيعة كلها تقريباً، بهذا الشكل...
I noticed that almost all the houses in the village are like
this...
يعني عندكم مساحة أرض ديار كثير واسعة ما شاء الله.
I mean, you have a very spacious courtyard area, Mashallah.
مزروعة ورد، مزروعة شجر، فيها كأنه جب مي؟
Planted with roses, planted with trees, does it have a water
well?
إي نعم.
Yes, indeed.
أنتم عندكم جب مي هون؟
Do you have a water well here?
عندنا جب مي، إي.
We have a water well, yes.
إي، لأنه المساحات هدول كانوا ملاكين، كل واحد من مساحة أرضه،
على راحته يعني...
Yes, because these areas belonged to landowners, each one
from the area of his land, at his own comfort, you know...
ما هو شري ولا شيء، فعنده مساحة الأحواش كبيرة يعني.
It wasn't bought or anything, so he has a large courtyard
space, you know.
شقد عمره هالبيت هذا تبعكم؟
How old is this house of yours?
تقريباً 55 سنة، 56 سنة.
Approximately 55 years, 56 years.
55، 56 سنة.
55, 56 years.
شيء كثير حلو.
Very beautiful thing.
مبين عليه تراثي و...
It looks heritage-like and...
قديم نعم، عماره قديم.
Old, yes, its architecture is old.
قديم. فيكي تعددي لي أنواع الورود والزهور والشجر اللي عندك
هون؟
Old. Can you list for me the types of roses, flowers, and
trees you have here?
والله هذا بيقولوا له شجرة الشمسية.
Well, this one they call the umbrella tree.
شمسية أو مظلة، نعم.
Umbrella or canopy, yes.
المظلة يعني. وفي ورد جوري وعندنا الجوزة، عندنا التفاح، عندنا
الرمان، عندنا البوملي...
The canopy, you know. And there are Damask roses, and we
have a walnut tree, we have apples, we have pomegranates, we
have pomelo...
عندنا الكرمة.
We have the grapevine.
والزرعات؟ شفت عندك هون ريحان، شفت عندك...
And the plants? I saw you have basil here, I saw you have...
في ريحان، في هي المكحلة بيقولوا لها، في ورق ليمون...
There is basil, there is this one they call 'Makahla', there
are lemon leaves...
عندنا اللادنكية، عندنا الزنبقة، بيقولوا لها ضراير...
We have the Ladanekia, we have the lily, they call it
'Dara'ir'...
إي هيك شغلات.
Yes, things like that.
نحن كثير انبسطنا بجيتنا معكم ونحن بنعتذر لأنه فتحنا جروح عمي
أبو محمد.
We are very happy with our visit with you, and we apologize
because we opened Uncle Abu Muhammad's wounds.
لا أهلاً وسهلاً فيكم 100 سلامة، شرفتونا.
No, you are very welcome, a hundred greetings, you honored
us.
الله يكرمكم. الله يعطيك العافية عمي أبو محمد.
May God honor you. May God give you health, Uncle Abu
Muhammad.
أهلاً وسهلاً، أهلاً.
Welcome, welcome.
أنا بعتذر.
I apologize.
لا، لا.
No, no.
الله يفرج عليكم يا رب.
May God bring you relief, O Lord.
أمين يا رب، أمين.
Amen, O Lord, Amen.
الله يفرج عالجميع يا رب.
May God bring relief to everyone, O Lord.
أمين أهلاً وسهلاً.
Amen, welcome.
علينا وعليكم.
Upon us and upon you.
أعزائي المشاهدين، انتهت جولتنا هذه التي قدمناها لكم من قرية
الشيخ عبد الرحمن...
Dear viewers, our tour that we presented to you from the
village of Sheikh Abdul Rahman...
التابعة لناحية جنديرس، منطقة عفرين في ريف حلب الشمالي.
Belonging to the Jindires sub-district, Afrin region in the
northern countryside of Aleppo.
سنكون معكم في جولات جديدة من مناطق سورية جميلة وحبيبة.
We will be with you in new tours from beautiful and beloved
Syrian regions.
لمتابعة برنامجنا تابعوا صفحة الفيس الخاصة بالقناة وأيضاً
موقعنا على الإنترنت...
To follow our program, follow the channel's Facebook page
and also our website...
حلب تودي تي في دوت نت.
Aleppotodaytv.net.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace be upon you, and the mercy of God and His blessings.
[Musiq]
[Outro Music]
[Music Fades]